<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Two speeches of Mr. James Guthry before the Parliament one after the reading of his indictment, Feb. 21, 1661, the other immediately after the reading of the processe, April 10, 1661.</title>
            <author>Guthrie, James, 1612?-1661.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1661</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 38 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A42360</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G2267A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R12166</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11998224</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11998224</idno>
            <idno type="VID">52167</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A42360)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 52167)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 564:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Two speeches of Mr. James Guthry before the Parliament one after the reading of his indictment, Feb. 21, 1661, the other immediately after the reading of the processe, April 10, 1661.</title>
                  <author>Guthrie, James, 1612?-1661.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1661.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Guthrie, James, 1612?-1661.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:52167:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>TWO SPEECHES OF Mr. <hi>JAMES GUTHRY</hi> BEFORE THE PARLIAMENT.</p>
            <p>One after the reading of his INDICTMENT, <hi>Feb.</hi> 21. 1661.</p>
            <p>The other immediately after the reading of the PROCESSE, <hi>April</hi> 10. 1661.</p>
            <p>Printed in the Year, 1661.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="21 February 1661" type="speech">
            <pb facs="tcp:52167:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:52167:2"/>
            <head>Mr. <hi>James Guthry</hi> his Speech before the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, after the reading of his Indict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>Febr.</hi> 21. 1661.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord Chancellour,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eing Indicted at the inſtance of Sir <hi>John Fles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher,</hi> his Majeſties Advocate, for his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Intereſt, upon things alledged to be Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditious and Treaſonable, I do humbly deſire, and from your equity expect, that my Lord Commiſſioner his Grace, and this Honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Court of Parliament, will patiently, and without interruption, allow me hearing, as to a few things which I have to ſay for my ſelf, in anſwer to that Indictment, and that I may proceed diſtinctly therein, following the order of the Indictment it ſelf, I ſhall ſpeak a word firſt to the Laws that are mentioned and cited therein, by which I am to be judged, then to the things themſelves whereof I am accuſed: Concerning theſe Laws, I am glad that the Law of God is named in the firſt place, it being indeed the Soveraign and Supreme Law, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of Religion, but alſo of righteouſneſs, to which all other Laws ought to be ſquared and ſubordinate; and there being an Act of the 1. Parl<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of K. <hi>Ja.</hi> 6. whereby all Laws, or clauſes of Laws, or Acts of Parliament, repugnant unto the Word of God, are repealed, an Act moſt worthy of a Chriſtian King and Kingdome; and I hope that your Lordſhip, in all your pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, will moſtly have reſpect unto this, that I may be judged by the Law of God eſpecially, and by other Laws in ſubordination thereunto. As to theſe Laws and Acts of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which are mentioned in the Indictment, concerning his Majeſties Royal Prerogative, and declining his Majeſties Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Authority, and keeping of Conventions: I hope it
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:52167:3"/>will not be denied, that they are to be underſtood and explained according to that ſenſe and meaning that is gre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> thereof by poſterior Acts of Parliament, it being a maxime in the Law, no leſs common, then true and equitable, that where there is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſeeming or real contradiction and oppoſition betwixt Laws,
<hi>Poſteriora derogant prioribus,</hi> otherwayes Laws, inſtead of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervatives to States and Commonwealths, might prove nets and ſnares, to intangle the lives, reputations, and eſtates of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects. And it muſt alſo be granted, that theſe Laws and Acts of Parliament, are to be underſtood and expounded by our ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn publick Vows and Covenants contracted with God, both by his Majeſty and Subjects, which are not only declared by the Laws of the Land to have the ſtrength of Acts of Parliament, but both by the Law of God, and Common-Law, and light of all the Nations in the world, are more binding and indiſpenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, then any municipal Law or Statute whatſoever. Thirdly, as to theſe Acts of Parliament, which are cited ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap> ſlander<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and untrue ſpeeches, to the diſdain, contempt and reproach of his Majeſties Authority, I think I need not ſay that none, much leſs his Majeſties Commiſſioner, and this Honourable Court of Parliament, do underſtand them of truths uttered in ſobriety, by thoſe who have any lawful call thereunto; and that theſe Acts, which ſpeak againſt medling in the affairs of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty and States, are not to be underſtood of ſuch medling, as men are bound unto by virtue of their calling, and wherein they do not tranſgreſs the bounds thereof. The next thing I ſhall ſpeak to, is the particulars wherewith I am charged, concerning which, I ſhall give your Lordſhip a true and ingenuous ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt, as to my acceſſion thereto, knowing that I ſpeak in the ſight of him who ſits in the Aſſembly of the Gods: Next, I ſhall be bold to offer to your Lordſhip ſome humble defence of my doing for vindica<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing of my carriage from the breach of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Laws, and exempting me from the puniſhment appointed thereby: As to matter of fact, I am in the Indictment firſt char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged with a general, of being culpable of ſundry ſeditious and treaſonable Remonſtrances, Declarations, Petitions, Inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Letters, Speeches, Preachings, Declamations, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> To which I ſay, that <hi>generalia non pungunt,</hi> they can have no ſtrength in the inferring of any crime of guilt, except in ſo far as they are
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:52167:3"/>inſtanced and verified in particulars, but are like unto that uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal, that having no foundation in <hi>re,</hi> is a meer Chimera, or ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond notion, only one thing there is in that general charge that I cannot, yea ought not to paſs by, to wit, that I have ſeditiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and trayterouſly purpoſed the eradicating and ſubverting the Fundamental Government of this his Majeſties ancient King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, at leaſt the enervating, or violating, or impairing of his Authority; concerning which, I am bold to ſay it is an unjuſt Charge, there was never any ſuch deſign or purpoſe in my heart; and ſince I am thus charged, I may without vanity, or the breach of the law of ſobriety affirm, that as I had never any complyances with the counſel, deſigns, or actings of the late uſurping Powers againſt his Majeſties Royal Father, or himſelf, or againſt this Kingdome, or the ancient Government thereof, or of the Kingdomes of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> ſo was there no part of their ungodly &amp; unjuſt actings, but I did in my ſtation &amp; calling bear open and publick teſtimony againſt the ſame, both by word and writ, which is a thing better known, and more ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, then that can be liable to ſuſpition therein, many of theſe teſtimonies being given before many, and many of them being yet extant in the world, and ſuch as will be extant to poſterity. My Lord, albeit it doth become me to adore God in the holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and wilſdome of his diſpenſations, yet I can hardly refrain from expreſſing ſome grief of ſpirit, that my houſe and family ſhould not only have been poſſeſt for many moneths together by a number of Engliſh ſouldiers, and my ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f kept from the Pulpit for ſpeaking and preaching againſt the tender and incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porating of this Nation in one Commonwealth with <hi>England,</hi> and that I ſhould thereafter, in the time of <hi>Oliver Cromwell,</hi> as uſurping the Government to himſelf, under the name of Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor, been delated by ſome, and challenged by ſundry of his Councel in this Nation, becauſe of a paper publiſhed by me, wherein he was declared to be an Uſurper, and his Government to be Uſurpation, that I ſhould have been threatned to be ſent to the Tower for writing a paper againſt <hi>Oliver Cromwell,</hi> his U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurping of the Crown of theſe Kingdomes; that I ſhould have been threatned with baniſhment, for concurring in offering a large teſtimony againſt the evils of the time to <hi>Richard Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well</hi> his Councel, immediately after his uſurping of the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:52167:4"/>I ſay, my Lord, it grieves me, that notwithſtanding of theſe things, I ſhould now ſtand indicted before your Lordſhip, as intending the eradicating and ſubverting of the ancient Civil Government of this Nation, and beign ſubſervient to that Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per in his deſigns, the God of heaven knows, that I am free of this Charge; and I do defie all the world, allowing me Juſtice and fair proceeding, which I hope your Lordſhip will, to make out the ſame againſt me. The firſt particular wherewith I am charged in the Indictment is, that I did contrive, and comply, and draw up ane paper, commonly called <hi>The Remonſtrance,</hi> and preſented it, or cauſed it to be preſented to his Majeſty, and the Committee of Eſtates, upon the 22 day of <hi>October,</hi> 1650. To which I anſwer, by denying that part of the Indictment, I did neither compile, nor contrive that Remonſtrance, nor did I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, nor cauſed it to be preſented to the Committee of Eſtates, at that time, or at any other time; I did indeed, being a Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Commiſſion of the Gen. Aſſembly, when they gave their judgement upon it, diſſent from the ſentence which they paſt upon it, which cannot be reckoned any culpable acceſſion thereto, every man being free, without hazard of puniſhment, and bound in conſcience, as before God, to give his judgement freely in the Judicatory whereof he is a Member: If it be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged, that I did afterwards abate the ſame in the book of the Cauſes of the Lords wrath, in the ſixth head of the nin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle thereof, by aſſerting the rejecting of the diſcovery of guiltineſs contained therein, to have been a ſin, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is anſwered firſt, that that was no more but the aſſerting of my former diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent: Secondly, that it was no more, upon the matter, then was acknowledged and aſſerted by the whole Commiſſion of the Gen. Aſſembly, when they paſt ſentence upon it, in which ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence it is acknowledged, that it did contain many ſad truths, which yet were not received, nor any effectual remedy endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured for helping of evils repreſented thereby. Thirdly, it cannot be accompted culpable in a Miniſter of the Goſpel, who is thereunto bound by virtue of his calling, to aſſert the rejecting of the diſcovery of ſin, and guiltineſs to be a ſin. The next particular which I am charged with, is the book of the Cauſe of Gods Controverſie, eſpecially the fifth and ſixth Articles there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, which are particulars that I believe, upon the looking there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, will not be found to contain any juſt matter of accuſation,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:52167:4"/>much leſs matter of ſedition and Treaſon, there being nothing mentioned therein, but the diſcovery of the ſin of covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and the abuſe of the publick Faith of the Land in bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowing of money; but becauſe I do apprehend that it was the fifth and ſixth ſtep of the ninth Article that was intended by my Lord Advocate, I do humbly profeſs unto your Lordſhip, and to this Honourable Court of Parliament, that I am very unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly drawn forth to ſpeak of theſe things, and ſhall only ſay firſt, That the God of heaven is witneſs, that my acceſſion thereunto, it did not flow from any diſreſpect or disaffection to his Majeſties perſon or Government, much leſs from any mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious purpoſe to render him odious to the world, or to his Subjects, or to give advantage to his enemies, and the enemies of theſe Kingdomes, or from any purpoſe in any thing to be ſubſervient to the deſigns or actings of the late uſurping powers, but meerly and ſingly from a conſtraining power of conſcience to be found faithful as a Miniſter of the Coſpel in the diſcovery of ſin and guiltineſs, that it being taken with, and repented of, wrath might be taken away from the houſe of the King, and from theſe Kingdomes: Your Lordſhip knows what ſtrict charge is laid upon Miniſters of the Goſpel to give faithful warning to all ſorts of perſons, and how they expoſe their own ſouls to the hazard of eternal damnation, and the guilt of the blood of thoſe with whom they have to do, if they do not; and you do alſo know, that the Prophets and Apoſtles, and the Lord Jeſus Chriſt himſelf, did faithfully warn all men, though it was their lot, becauſe of the ſame, to be reckoned Traytors, and ſeditious perſons, and to ſuffer as evil doers upon the accompt thereof. Next, my Lord, I wiſh it may be ſeriouſly pondered, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is aſſerted in theſe cauſes as to the matter of ſin and duty, but what hath been the common received doctrine of the Kirk of <hi>Scotland,</hi> as may appear from the Records of the work of Reformation from Popery, and from the National Covenant, and Solemn League and Covenant, and the publick Declarations and Acts of this Kirk and Kingdome, concerning the neceſſary ſecurity of Religion; the truth of which doctrine is confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from the Word of God, and divine reaſon, in theſe publick papers themſelves; and as to matters of fact, they are no other then is mentioned in the ſolemn publick cauſes of humiliation,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:52167:5"/>condeſcended and kept either by the whole Kirk of <hi>Scotland</hi> joyntly, and by his Majeſty and his family, with the Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the General-Aſſembly, and the Committee of Eſtates, a little before his Coronation at <hi>Perth.</hi> As to the ſixth ſtep, there is nothing therein mentioned but what is truth, all the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars therein ſpecified, as of the Remonſtrance it ſelf, contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſome diſcovery of known and undeniable ſins and guiltineſs, the rejecting whereof behoved to be a ſin, and therefore can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not the aſſerting of it be Treaſon and Sedition. The third par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular wherewith I am charged, is the ſupplication at <hi>Oſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gust</hi> 24. To which I acknowledge my acceſſion, but do deny it to be treaſonable and ſeditious, becauſe beſides the vindication of my former carriage and actings from complyances with the late uſurping powers, and an humble profeſſion of that ſubjecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and loyalty, and obedience, which I owe to his Majeſty and of my reſolution to render the ſame unto him, as unto the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme and rightful Magiſtrate over theſe Kingdomes, and ſome ſerious prayers and ſupplications for his Majeſty, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain nothing but an humble Petition concerning theſe things, to which his Majeſty and all the Subjects of this Kingdome are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged by the ſolemn and indiſpenſable Oath of the Covenant, with a ſober and ſerious repreſentation of the dangers that threaten Religion, and of things that are deſtructive unto the duties contained in theſe Articles of the Covenant; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Covenant being eſtabliſhed by Law, and conſtrained by the publick Oath of God, which is more then Law, a humble Petition and Repreſentation concerning theſe things, cannot be accompted Sedition and Treaſon. The Indictment is pleaſed to ſay, that I charged his Majeſty with diſſimulation and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury, but there is no ſuch thing in the ſupplication, which doth only put him in remembrance of holding faſt the oath of the Covenant: As to what is alledged againſt the unlawfulneſs of our meeting, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> was Presbyterially reſolved, that I ſhould keep that meeting, and ſuppoſe it had not been ſo, yet cannot that meeting fall within the compaſs of theſe Acts of Parliament, which ſtrikes againſt unlawful Conventions, becauſe every meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for buſineſs in it ſelf, lawful or agreeable to the Word of God, and the Laws of the Land, and keeped without multitude or tumult, ſuch as that was, needs no particular Warrant from
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:52167:5"/>Authority, as may be inſtanced in ſundry other meetings up and down the Land, day by day, for ſeveral ſorts of buſineſs: Be there not many meetings kept by perſons of all ſorts in all the parts of the Country, in reference to applications to Judicato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and to the Supreme Magiſtrate, for the civil intereſts and rights? and if ſo, how much more may Miniſters meet for ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicating his Majeſty, for the intereſts and right of Jeſus Chriſt, keeping themſelves for the matter of their ſupplication within the bounds of the Covenant, and of theſe things that are eſtabliſhed by Law.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, ſuch meetings are clearly exempted from the breach of theſe Acts of
<hi>Parliament,</hi> by a poſterior Act of Parliament, to wit, by the 29th Act of the 2 Parl. of King <hi>Charles</hi> the firſt.</p>
            <p>As to the laſt particular in the Indictment, to wit, my decli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of his Majeſties Authority at <hi>Perth,</hi> I do acknowledg, that I did decline the Civil Magiſtrate, as competent Judge of Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters Doctrine in the firſt inſtant; his Majeſties Authority, in all things civil, I do with all my heart acknowledge, and that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Confeſſion of the Faith of this Church, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation and purgation of Religion belongs to him as civil Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate, and that Eccleſiaſtick perſons are not exempted from obedience to Civil Authority, and the juſt commands thereof, not from puniſhment in caſe of their tranſgreſſion; but that declinators of the Civil Magiſtrate, his being Judge of Miniſters Doctrine in the firſt inſtant, are no treaſon nor ſedition, but lawful and warrantable: I do humbly offer firſt, that ſuch decli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nators are agreeable to the rule of Gods Word, and to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions of Faith and Doctrine of this Church, which are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed and ratified in Parliament by many ſeveral Acts, and therefore have the ſtrength both of divine and humane Law; that they are agreeable to the rule of Gods Word, is evidents from this that the Scriptures do clearly hold forth, that Jeſus Chriſt hath a viſible Kingdome, which he exerciſes in or over his viſible Church, by the ſpiritual office bearers thereof, which is wholly diſtinct from the civil powers and government of the world, and not depending upon, nor ſubordinate unto theſe go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernments, and the Acts thereof, <hi>John</hi> 18.36, 37. <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.19.
<hi>John</hi> 28.23.</p>
            <p>That they are agreeable to the Confeſſions of Faith and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:52167:6"/>of this Church is evident, becauſe theſe do acknowledge no Head over the viſible Church of Chriſt, but Jeſus Chriſt himſelf, nor any Judgement, nor Power, in nor over his houſe, but that which he hath committed unto the ſpiritual office-bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers thereof under himſelf; and therefore it hath been the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary practiſe of this Church in ſuch caſes, to uſe ſuch decli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nators, ſince the time of Reformation from Popery, as may appear from many clear, and undeniable, and proven inſtances, extant in the Acts of the Gen. Aſſemblies, and Records of this Church, particularly theſe of Mr. <hi>David Black,</hi> in the year 1596. which was owned and ſubſcribed by three or four hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Miniſters, beſides ſundry others which are well known; and I do believe, my Lord, that not only is this the doctrine of the Church of <hi>Scotland,</hi> but alſo of many ſound Proteſtant Divines, who give unto
<hi>Caeſar</hi> the things that are <hi>Caeſars,</hi> and to God the things that are Gods. Secondly, ſuch declinators are agreeable unto, and founded upon the National Covenant, and the Solemn League and Covenant, by which the Kings Majeſty himſelf, and all the Subjects of this Kingdome are bound to maintain the doctrine, worſhip, diſcipline, and govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this Church, which with ſolemn vows, and publick Oaths of God, have alwayes in all Kingdomes, States, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publicks, been accompted more ſacred and binding, then any municipal Law or Statute whatſoever, and being poſterior to the Act of Parliament 1584. do neceſſarily include a repealing thereof: Upon theſe grounds it is, that I gave in, and do aſſert that declinator, for vindicating the Crown dignity, and Royal Prerogative of Jeſus Chriſt, who is King of Kings, and Lord of Lords, but with all due reverence and reſpect to his Majeſty, and his juſt greatneſs and Authority.</p>
            <p>Fourthly; as to that Act of Parliament 1584. was made in a time wherein the ſetled Government of this Church by Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters and Synods, was wholly over-turned, and their meetings utterly diſcharged, and the depoſition of Miniſters and things properly ſpiritual and Eccleſiaſtick, put into the hands of the Civil Magiſtrate, ſo we do aſſert, that that Act, in ſo far as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns ſuch declinators, hath ſince the making thereof been of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten repealed and reſcinded, and was ſtanding repealed and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcinded at the down ſitting of the Parliament: Firſt, it was ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſed
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:52167:6"/>and annulled by a poſterior Act, in the year 1592. to wit, the firſt Act of the 12. Parl. of King <hi>Ja.</hi> the 6. which in the laſt Section thereof, doth expreſly declare, that that Act in the year 1584. ſhall no wayes be prejudicial, nor derogate any thing to the priviledge that God has given to the ſpiritual office-bearers in the Kirk, concerning heads of Religion, matters of Hereſie, collation or deprivation of Miniſters, or any ſick-like eſſential cenſure, ſpecially grounded and having Warrant from the Word of God; but ſo it is, that the freedome and indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency of the ſpiritual office-bearers of the Kirk of God in things Eccleſiaſtical, that concern their calling, is a ſpecial pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge of the Kirk, and a ſpecial head of Religion, and that the free diſcovering of the ſins of all perſons by Miniſters in their Doctrine from the word of God, is an eſſential cenſure ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon, and having warrant in the Word of God; and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording hereto King <hi>James</hi> the 6. in the year
1585. conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the great offence given and taken by that Act in the year 84. did for removing thereof, ſend a Declaration penned and ſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with his own hand to the Commiſſioners of the Kirk of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> at <hi>Linlithgow, Decemb.</hi> 7. which he ſayes ſhall be as good and valid, as any Act of Parliament whatſoever. In which De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration he hath theſe words,
<hi>I for my part ſhall never, neither my Poſterity ought ever cite, ſummon, or apprehend any Paſtor or Preacher, for matters of Doctrine, Religion, Salvation, Hereſies, or ton interpretation of the Scriptures, but according to my firſt Act, which confirmeth the liberty of preaching of the Word, Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of the Sacraments, &amp;c. I avouch the ſame to be a matter meer Eccleſiaſtical, and altogether impertinent to my calling, therefore never ſhall I, nor never ought they, I mean my poſterity, acclaim any power or Juriſdiction in the foreſaids.</hi> It is alſo to be conſidered, that that Act 1584. is alſo repealed by the
4th Act of the 2d Parl. of King <hi>Charles</hi> the 1. which reckons it amongſt the evils that had ſore troubled the peace of the Church and Kingdome; that the power of the Keys and Kirk-cenſures was given to perſons meerly civil, and therefore doth provide, that for preſervation of Religion, and preventing all ſuch evils in time coming, Gen. Aſſemblies rightly conſtitute, as the proper and competent Iudges of all matters Eccleſiaſtical hereafter, be keeped yearly, and oftner, <hi>pro re naia,</hi> as occaſion and neceſſity ſhall require. The ſame Act in the year 1584: is alſo repealed
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:52167:7"/>by the 6th Act of the 2d Parl. of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Act reſciſſory, which expreſly provides and declares, that the ſole, and only power, and juriſdiction within this Kirk, ſtands in the Kirk of God, as it is now reformed, and in the General, Provincial, Presbyterial Aſſemblies, with Kirk Seſſions, eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed by Act of Parliament in <hi>Jan.</hi> 1592. which Act is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly revived, and renewed in the whole heads, points, and Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles in the foreſaid Act reſciſſory, and is appointed to ſtand in full ſtrength, as a perpetual Law in a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l time coming, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of whatſoever Acts or Statutes made in the contrary thereof, in whole or in part, which the Eſtates by that Act re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciſſory caſſes and annulls in all time coming, and reſcinds and annulls all and whatſoever Acts of Parliament, Laws and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions, in ſo far as they derogate, and are prejudicial to the ſpiritual nature, juriſdiction, diſcipline, and priviledges of this Kirk, by which it is evident, that not only that that Act in the year 1584. but alſo the firſt Act of the 18 Parl. of King <hi>James</hi> the 6th, and 3d Act of the firſt Parl. of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, whcih ratifies and eſtabliſhes the Royal Prerogative over all e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, perſons, and cauſes within this Kingdome, is declared to be of no force, in ſo far as the ſame may be extended to make the Supreme Magiſtrate the proper and competent Iudge of matters Spiritual and Eccleſiaſtick. Sixthly, it is to be obſerved, that it hath been lawful, and in continual practiſe, that his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty and ſecret Councel, in ſundry cauſes, have been declined, and the cauſe drawn to the ordinary competent Iudge; as mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters Civil to the Lords of the Seſſion, matters criminal to the Chief Iuſtice, matters of divorcement to the Commiſſaries, yea the meaneſt regality in the Country, hath power to decline the Supreme Iudicatories. As to what is alledged in the cloſe of the Indictment, of proteſting for remedy of Law againſt his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty for a ſeaſment, &amp;c. of that proteſtation, was but an Appendix and Conſequent of the other, made only in reference thereto, and a proteſtation againſt any particular Act for remedy accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his Majeſties Laws, cannot be treaſon againſt his Majeſty, there being no Act of Parliament declaring it to be ſo, and it being not Authority it ſelf that is proteſted againſt, but only a particular Act of the Authority, againſt which proteſtations in many caſes are ordinary. Laſtly, it is to be obſerved, that this declinatur was buried in ſilence by his Majeſty, and the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:52167:7"/>of Eſtates after the in-giving thereof, and M. <hi>Guthry</hi> ſent home without their challenging of him for the ſame, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted the exerciſe of his Miniſtry at
<hi>Sterling.</hi> Theſe few things, my Lord, I thought fit at preſent to ſay in vindication, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of my own innocency, notwithſtanding of any thing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the Indictment now read againſt me; the ſum of what I have ſaid is ſhortly in theſe two: firſt, that I did never purpoſe nor intend to ſpeak, or write, or act any thing diſloyal, or ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, or treaſonable, againſt his Majeſties perſon or Authority, or Government, God is my witneſs, and that what I have ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, or written, or acted in any of theſe things wherewith I am charged, hath been meerly and ſingly from a principle of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, that according to the weak meaſure of light given me of God, I might do my duty in my ſtation and calling, as a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of the Goſpel: Next, becauſe conſcience barely taken, is not a ſufficient plea, though it may extenuate, yet it cannot whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly excuſe, I do aſſert, that I have founded my ſpeeches, and wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, and actings in theſe matters upon the Word of God, and the Doctrine and Confeſſions of Faith, and Laws of this Church and Kingdome, and upon the National Covenant of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and the Solemn League and Covenant betwixt the three King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes of
<hi>Scotland, England,</hi> and <hi>Ireland;</hi> if theſe foundations ſhall fail, I muſt fall with them, but if theſe ſuſtain and ſtand in judgment, as I hope they will, I cannot acknowledge my ſelf, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, I hope, will his Majeſties Lord Commiſſioner, and the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable Court of Parliament, judg me guilty of ſedition and trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, notwithſtanding of any thing contained in the Indictment.</p>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>After this Speech before the Parliament, Mr.</hi> James Guthry <hi>was appointed to give in writing his legal defences, or what he had to ſay in Law for his own defence againſt the things contained in his Indictment, which legal defences he gave in to the Lord Advo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate, the fourth of</hi> March. <hi>Theſe defences contain five ſheets of paper, to which having received a Reply from the Lord Advocate, about fifteen daies thereafter, he did return a Duply thereunto the fifth of</hi> April, <hi>conſiſting of ſeven ſheets of paper; and being call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed before the Parliament the tenth of</hi> April, <hi>his whole Proceſs conſiſting of the Indictment, and his Defences, and the Lord Advo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates Reply was read; after which, having liberty to ſpeak again for himſelf, he did by word of mouth deliver what is contained in the following Speech.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
         </div>
         <div n="10 April 1661" type="speech">
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:52167:8"/>
            <head>Mr. <hi>James Guthry</hi> his Speech before the Parliament, immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after the reading of the Proceſs, <hi>April 10. 1661.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord Chancellour,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Did at my firſt appearance before his Majeſties Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oner, and this Honourable Court of Parliament, give an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt of my acceſſion to the particulars contained in the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictment, and of the grounds and reaſons thereof, and have now done it more fully in my Defences, and in my Duplies to the Replies given by my Lord Advocate thereunto, in all which I have dealt ingeniouſly, and without ſhifting, holding it the duty of a Chriſtian, eſpecially of a Miniſter of the Goſpel, in the matters of his duty and calling ſo to do; I have only now to add theſe few words.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That I hope I have made it ſufficiently to appear, that what I have ſpoke, or written, or acted in theſe matters, was from no malicious or ſiniſtrous intention againſt his Majeſties perſon, or his Government, but from a principle of true piety towards God, and true loyalty towards his Majeſty, as I have demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted this from the tenor of my carriage and actings under the U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurpers, ſo I have herein confidence towards God, and in the perſwaſion of the integrity of my Soul in this particular, may with a good conſcience, not only make this Declaration before your Lordſhip, but alſo hazard to ſtep into Eternity.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Next, my Lord, I hope I have made it to appear, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the conformity that my acceſſion to theſe things have with the Word of God, ſo they have a foundation in the National Covenant, and in the Solemn League and Covenant, the obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion whereof I dare not but profeſs to own, as binding and ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon theſe Kingdomes, and that they are agreeable unto the actings of publick Authority, before the Engliſhes invading of this Nation, to the Canons of the Church, and the Laws of the Kingdome, and the publick declared judgment both of Church and State before that time: And my Lord, if this may not plead an Indempnity and Oblivion for me, but that notwithſtanding thereof I ſhall be judged a ſeditious perſon and a Traytor, not only ſhall the whole Church and Kingdome of <hi>Scotland</hi> be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volved in the guilt of Sedition and Treaſon, and few or none have any ſecurity for their lives, and honours, and eſtates, fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:52167:8"/>then the Kings mercy doth give them; but alſo a very dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous foundation ſhall be laid for the time to come, for men of differing judgments, upon every emergent revolution, to proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute the worſted party unto death, notwithſtanding that they have the publick Authority, and the Laws then ſtanding, to plead in the defence of their actings. I know my Lord, that it lyeth upon the ſpirits of ſome, as a prejudice againſt me, that I am ſuppoſed to have been a chief inſtrument, or a Ring-leader, in theſe Declarations, and Canons, and Laws, and publick actings of the Church and Kingdome, which I do now plead in my own defence: I ſhall not ſay, that this hath any riſe from any, who to lighten their own burthens, would en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe mine, holding that to be unworthy of any man of an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genious ſpirit, and moſt unworthy of a Chriſtian: As I charge no man in particular with acceſſion to any of theſe things, ſo as to my ſelf, I do for the truths ſake ingenuouſly acknowledge, that throughout the whole courſe of my life I have ſtudied to be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, and to deal not with a ſlack hand in what I did look upon as my duty; and yet my Lord, leſt I ſhould attribute unto my ſelf what is not due unto me, I muſt, for ſhunning of pride and vain-glory alſo ſay, that I was not honoured to be of theſe who laid the firſt foundation of the work of Reformation in this Church and Kingdome: I am not aſhamed to give glory to God in acknowledging, that until the beginning of the year 1638. I was tread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing other ſteps, and though God did then graciouſly recover me out of the ſnare of Prelacy, and the Ceremonies and Service-book, and a little thereafter put me into the Miniſtry, yet did I never judge my ſelf worthy to be accompted a Ring-leader in any of the ſuperſtructures of that bleſſed work, there being a good many elder for years, and more eminent for pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and prudence, and parts, and faithfulneſs, and zeal, whom I did reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, and gave the precedency unto in theſe things.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It may alſo happily my Lord be, and a little I have been informed of it, that beſides any thing contained in the Indictment, there be ſome other things that bear weight upon the ſpirits of ſome of the Members of this Houſe, from reports that have paſſed of my carriage towards his Majeſties Royal Father, and towards himſelf, and ſome others. As to theſe things, my Lord, if there be any thing of that kind, I do moſt humbly and ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly beg, and think that I may juſtly expect, both in order to Juſtice, and to the peace of their own conſciences, that ſeeing they have no proof of it, but at beſt have taken it upon information, that they would either al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together lay it aſide, and lay no weight upon it, or elſe before they give Judgment of me, they would let me know of it, and allow me a fair hearing upon it, and if I cannot vindicate my ſelf, let me bear the burdning of it.</p>
            <p n="4">4. In the next place, my Lord, knowing that it is wondred and offended
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:52167:9"/>at, not by a few of the Members of this Parliament, that I ſhould ſtand to my own juſtification in the things whereof I am challenged, and that this I looked upon as a piece of peremptory and wilful humour, which if I plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, I might eaſily lay aſide. My Lord, I humbly beg ſo much charity of all who now hear me, as to think, that I have not ſo far loſt the exerciſe of all conſcience towards God, and of all reaſon towards my ſelf, and my deareſt relations in the world, as upon deliberation to hazard, if not caſt away, both my life and ſoul at once, God knows it is not humour, but conſcience that ſticks with me, and could I lay it aſide and not ſin againſt God, not diſſemble with men, by confeſſing or profeſſing what I think not, I ſhould not ſtand to the defence of any of theſe things for the minute of an hour: but my Lord, having with prayer and ſupplication unto the God of truth, ſearched the Word of God, and conſulted the judgement and practiſe of the Reformed Churches, eſpecially of our own Church, ſince the time of Reformation from Popery, and writings of many ſound and Orthodox Divines, and having frequently converſed and conferred with the godly Miniſtry and praying people of this Nation, and try the pulſe of their ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits anent the National Covenant, and the Solemn League and Covenant, the particulars contained in them, and ſuperſtructures that have been built upon them, anent ſin and duty, and the power of the Civil Magiſtrate in matters Spiritual and Eccleſiaſtical, I find my practiſe and profeſſion anent theſe things agreeable unto all theſe, and therefore cannot reckon my light for humour and deluſion, but muſt hold it faſt, until better guides be ſhown me to follow.</p>
            <p n="5">5. My Lord, I ſhall in the laſt place humbly beg, that having brought ſo pregnant and clear defences from the Word of God, ſo much divine rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and humane Law, and ſo much of the common practiſe of Kirk and King done in my own defence, and being already caſt out of my Miniſtry, thruſt out from my dwelling and maintenance, my ſelf and my family put to live upon the charity of others, and having now ſuffered eight moneths impriſonment, your Lordſhip would not put more burdnings upon me I ſhall conclude, my Lord, with the words of the Prophet
<hi>Jeremy</hi> in a like caſe, <hi>Behold,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>I am in your hands, do with me what ſeemeth good unto you;</hi> but know ye for certain, that the Lord hath commanded me to ſpeak all theſe things, and that if you put me to death, you ſhall bring innocent blood upon your ſelves, and upon the inhabitants of this City. My Lord, my conſcience I cannot ſubmit, but this old crazy body, and mortal fleſh, I do ſubmit, to do with it whatſoever you will, whether by death or impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment, or baniſhment, or any thing elſe, only I beſeech you to ponder well what profit is in my blood; it is not the extinguiſhing of me, or of many others, that will extinguiſh the Covenant and work of Reformation ſince the year 1638. My blood<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> bondage, or baniſhment, will contribute more for propagation of theſe things, then my life or liberty could do, though I ſhould live for many years. I wiſh to my Lord Commiſſioners Grace, and to all your Lordſhips, a ſpirit of judgement, and wiſdome, and underſtanding, and of the fear of the Lord, that you may judge righteous judgement, in which he may have glory, and the King honour and happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſs, and your ſelves peace in the day of your accompts.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
